我在20世纪60年代还是个孩子。这是一个技术进步和伟大的时代
I was a child in the 1960s. It was a time of great technological progress and great
对技术的兴奋。也许当时最大的例子是人的空间
excitement about technologies. Perhaps the biggest example at that time was man's space
旅行。这是第一批宇航员进入太空的时候。当我长大的时候，就是这样
travel. It was the time when the first astronauts would go into space. When I grew up, it was
明确我想成为一名宇航员。
clear that I wanted to be an astronaut.
技术进步的另一个形象是机器人，而此时，主要是机器人
The other image of technological progress was robots and at this time, there were mostly
小说中的机器人。在电视上，当我还是一个孩子长大的时候，其中有很多。
robots in fiction. On television, when I was a child growing up, there were many of these.
然而，早期有许多小说中的机器人描述，也许是第一个
However, there were many earlier depictions of robots in fiction, perhaps the first one
是1927年电影“大都会”中的人物玛丽亚。1951年的机器人Gort，
is the character Maria from the 1927 movie Metropolis. The robot Gort from the 1951,
电影的原创作品“地球静止之日”。那么也许，我的
the original make of the movie “The Day the Earth Stood Still”. Then perhaps, my
1956年电影“禁忌星球”中他最喜欢的机器人罗比出现在
all time favourite robot Robby from the movie Forbidden Planet in 1956 and he appeared in
其他一些后续电影。毫无疑问，这两个最着名的虚构机器人
a number of other follow-up movies. Without doubt, the two most famous fictional robots
这两部是原始的星球大战电影，它于1977年首次亮相，R2D2和他的
are these two from the original Star Wars movie, which debuted in 1977, R2D2 and his
健谈的朋友C3PO。
talkative friend C3PO.
这两个角色描绘了机器人是良性的。这对周围的人有帮助
These two characters depict robots as being benign. That is helpful to the people around
他们也非常聪明，能够用人类语言进行对话
them and also as being incredibly intelligent, able to hold conversations in human languages
并能够执行复杂的工程任务，如黑客入侵死星。
and being able to perform complex engineering tasks like hacking a Death star.
这部最近的电影机器人和弗兰克描绘了一个非常合理的未来，一个老人
This more recent movie Robot and Frank depicts a very plausible future where an old person
辅助机器人正在协助他们的日常生活，这是一个人形机器人
is being assisted in their daily life by a helper robot and this is a robot that is humanoid
在形式上，能够用自然语言与主角弗兰克交谈，引导他吃饭
in form, able to converse with the main character Frank in natural language, guide him to eat
更好，并改变他的一些坏习惯。
better and to change some of his bad habits.
但是，我们在小说中看到的所有机器人就是这样。他们是虚构的。所以，机器人
However, all robots that we see in fiction are just that. They are fiction. So, the robot
从大都会电影的方式回到1927年，确实是一个金属西装里面的人。
from the Metropolis movie way back in 1927 was indeed a human being inside a metallic suit.
你认为，1927年的技术真的很漂亮也许并不奇怪
You think, well that is probably not surprising that technology back in 1927 was really pretty
原始但它实际上没有太大变化。在20世纪50年代，机器人罗比也是人类
primitive but it hasn't actually changed much. In the 1950s, Robby the robot was also a human
在一个大金属套装里面。
being inside a large metallic suit.
所以，即使在最初的星球大战电影中，C3PO也是演员安东尼丹尼尔斯
So, it goes even in the original Star Wars movies C3PO was the actor Anthony Daniels
在金色金属套装里面。因此，对于R2D2来说，R2D2中的演员肯尼贝克也是如此。
inside a gold metallic suit. So, it also was for R2D2 the actor Kenny Baker inside R2D2.
自星球大战电影专营权开始以来，很多其他电影都有
Since the beginning of the Star Wars movie franchise very many, many other movies have
出来并向我们介绍特定的机器人角色，并描绘了他们的一些名字
come out and introduced us to particular robot characters and some of their names are depicted
这是时间的函数。
here as a function of time.
事实上，您可能会惊讶地发现您认为自己知道或认识的机器人数量。我喜欢这个
In fact, you might be surprise how many robots you think you know or recognize. I love this
特别的漫画，由RichardSergeant提供，展示了各种各样的虚构机器人和
particular cartoon, by Richard Sergeant which shows a wide range of fictional robots and
这是一个有趣的练习，看看你能辨认出多少机器人
it is an interesting exercise to go through this and see how many robots you can recognize
在这个场景中。这些解决方案可在网上获得。
in this scene. The solutions are available on the web.
除了电视和电影中机器人的所有描绘之外，还有
In addition to all the portrayals of robots in television and movies, there have also
大量的书籍，科幻小说都以机器人为主题
been a large number of books, Science fiction books which are based on the theme of robots
和机器人和人类之间的相互作用，良好的互动和不良的互动。
and interactions between robots and humanity, both good interactions and bad interactions.
机器人这个词本身就是捷克语，它意味着像工人或奴隶这样的东西
The word robot itself is a Czech word and it means something like worker or slave and
它是由捷克剧作家卡雷尔·卡佩克（KarelCapek）于1920年创作的。他的戏剧名为
it was coined in a 1920 play by the Czech playwright, Karel Capek. His play was titled
罗森的通用机器人或RUR。该剧的主题是人们创造机器人
Rossum's Universal Robot or RUR. The theme of the play is that people create robots to
减轻他们日常体力劳动的苦差事。机器人最终得到了反感
relieve them of the drudgery of everyday physical work. The robots eventually get to resent
他们在社会中的角色是做所有工作的人。他们起来了，他们反叛
their role in society as being the ones who do all the work. They rise up, they rebel
他们杀了人类。所以，这是许多机器人中非常反复出现的主题
and they kill the human beings. So, this is a very recurrent theme in many many robot
电影是在这一天制作的。我们可以把它想象成一种重新解释
movies being made to this very day. We can think of it perhaps as a reinterpretation
至少在此之前的一百年里，弗兰肯斯坦的故事。
of the story of Frankenstein from at least a hundred years before this.
几年前我有机会到布拉格，我去了并表达了我的敬意
I had the opportunity to be in Prague a few years ago and I went and paid my respects
去了KarelCapek，我去了他的坟墓，这里有一张照片，我很高兴
to Karel Capek, I went and visited his grave and a photograph is shown here and I was delighted
看到有人在他的墓碑上留下了一个小模型机器人。我希望我有想过
to see it that somebody has left a small model robot on his headstone. I wish I had thought
这样做我自己。
of doing that myself.
也许最能在小说中推广机器人理念的作者是
Perhaps the author who has done the most to popularize the idea of robots in fiction is
艾萨克·阿西莫夫（IsaacAsimov），一位非常非常多产的美国科幻作家。一个关键要素
Isaac Asimov, a very, very prolific American writer of Science fiction. A key element of
几乎所有阿西莫夫的故事都是他的机器人法则。在他的故事机器人中，这些
almost all of Asimov's stories are his laws of robotics. In robots in his stories, these
每个机器人的正电脑都嵌入了法则。机器人无能为力
laws were imbedded in the positronic brain of every robot. The robots were incapable
违反任何这些法律。如果你看，这些法律在面值，他们都做了
of violating any of these laws. If you look, these laws at face value, they all make a
很有意义，虽然在阿西莫夫的大部分故事中，总有一些皱纹或角落的情况
lot of sense, though in most of Asimov's stories, there was always some wrinkle or corner case
在法律的实施，法律与人类或与人交往的方式
in the implementation of the laws, the way the laws interacted with human beings or with
其他机器人。
other robots.